<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://dchere.com/">
  <title>dchere posts</title>
  <subtitle>personal optinions on tech, development, and life</subtitle>
  <link href="https://dchere.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://dchere.com/"/>
  <updated>2023-11-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://dchere.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>David Cizek</name>
    <email>pleasegotowebsitetofindemail@dchere.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Packaging with personal touch</title>
    <link href="https://dchere.com/posts/packaging-fun/"/>
    <updated>2023-11-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://dchere.com/posts/packaging-fun/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Packaging With Personal Touch&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Trash and dance!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-dance-to-trash-Qpjy_ATDaC-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/packaging-dance-to-trash-Qpjy_ATDaC-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-dance-to-trash-Qpjy_ATDaC-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/packaging-dance-to-trash-Qpjy_ATDaC-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-dance-to-trash-Qpjy_ATDaC-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;951&quot; alt=&quot;Trash and dance&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m thinking about the designer of this packaging (a boring everyday snack, no fancy brand). What does it take to NOT use existing sign about &amp;quot;trash it&amp;quot; (least effort taken), but create something that can make someone who sees this easter eggs, smile?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was it only the designer who made a graphical joke? Maybe it was a joyful subversion against the otherwise not-much-inspiring requirements? (The whole packaging of this product is ok but not very entertaining, which probably has to be because of all legal requirements?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the manager participated? I doubt it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway - well done! I love it!💃&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update: another example:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-pribinacek-o-hgXeQ4iW-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/packaging-pribinacek-o-hgXeQ4iW-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-pribinacek-o-hgXeQ4iW-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/packaging-pribinacek-o-hgXeQ4iW-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-pribinacek-o-hgXeQ4iW-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;1781&quot; alt=&quot;Meow and trash it&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Love letter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotted by my daughter. It&#39;s a brilliant way to tell something (not only) about packaging. Being a customer who bought it - I&#39;m already in a good mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt; &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-love-letter-QhlMo-VQbr-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/packaging-love-letter-QhlMo-VQbr-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-love-letter-QhlMo-VQbr-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/packaging-love-letter-QhlMo-VQbr-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/packaging-love-letter-QhlMo-VQbr-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;1379&quot; alt=&quot;I was a handwritten loveletter once&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;I was a handwritten loveletter once&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this one was not a subversion or a great joke. It feels like a team of enthusiastic people who care and think about details (because they love it) and have the green light from management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👏🏻&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Developer experience is a common sense</title>
    <link href="https://dchere.com/posts/devex-common-sense/"/>
    <updated>2023-11-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://dchere.com/posts/devex-common-sense/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Developer experience - DevEx - DX&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m interested in DX. Why? I consider myself to be a developer. So I have first-hand experience with when DX works and when not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, it is frustrating. So. Much. Not because of technical problems. Developers usually love technical challenges. Surprisingly, they don&#39;t mind working on tight deadlines, if needed. What ruins their day (and productivity) is when they have to explain, again and again, what they need to develop and deliver software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine the restaurant - you will unlikely go somewhere where you had a bad experience. But you will frequently eat at the one where you feel good. You feel good because the staff is friendly and nice, not stressed or frustrated (and sure they have a good meal). You watch the place, and you see a well-functioning organism. The restaurant thrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone can more or less imagine what the chef needs. Developers&#39; needs are far from well-known. Misunderstanding, downplaying, or ignoring these needs is a sure way to ruin their experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good experience creates happiness and, in the organization, it enhances effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers usually don&#39;t meet customers, so why care about their experience? First of all, it is because of better effectivity, as discussed. Another good reason is that the software is everywhere. Crappy software sucks and frustrates - customers or internal users. No developer wants to make buggy software, same as no chef wants to make a bad meal. Give them good conditions - good experience - and it will work better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations care about their people, not only because they want to, for whatever human or social reasons, but because they see that having happy people around is usually more profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s go back to developer experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it complicated to start with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not when you have the big picture internalized - happy people bring more value to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rule is the same to achieve anything else (playing piano, running a marathon). Just do it, track it, and stick with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://dchere.com/posts/chat-gpt-dev-ex&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I had fun asking chat GPT as someone new to DX. GPT nicely summarized the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see that it&#39;s common sense. You do not have to spend a ridiculously high amount of money on it (well, you can, but 🤷🏻‍♂️)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It boils down to a few points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) &lt;strong&gt;You care&lt;/strong&gt; about developer experience (it seems a matter-of-fact, but sometimes it isn&#39;t),&lt;br&gt;
(2) you &lt;strong&gt;assign&lt;/strong&gt; it to someone who will be responsible for it and &lt;br&gt;
(3) &lt;strong&gt;enable&lt;/strong&gt; her to do it (people usually use the word &amp;quot;empower&amp;quot;).&lt;br&gt;
(4) &lt;strong&gt;Measure&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;enhance&lt;/strong&gt; (widely expressed as rinse&amp;amp;repeat).&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Sure, the most important requirement is having developers at your organization.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DX is not another fancy technique or methodology. It is simply about (developers&#39;) &lt;strong&gt;experience&lt;/strong&gt; (see the lower &#39;e&#39;) and how to enhance it. Because &lt;strong&gt;it brings more value to the organization&lt;/strong&gt;. It is a mindset, not prescribed &amp;quot;how to do it&amp;quot; (with some trademark or copyright attached).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bullshit Jobs (by David Graeber)</title>
    <link href="https://dchere.com/posts/book-bullshit-jobs/"/>
    <updated>2023-10-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://dchere.com/posts/book-bullshit-jobs/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Book: Bullshit Jobs by David Graeber&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/book_bullshit_jobs-8BLDabyadN-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/book_bullshit_jobs-8BLDabyadN-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/book_bullshit_jobs-8BLDabyadN-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/book_bullshit_jobs-8BLDabyadN-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/book_bullshit_jobs-8BLDabyadN-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;1536&quot; alt=&quot;Book: Bullshit Jobs - David Graeber&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year ago, I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dawn_of_Everything&quot;&gt;The Dawn of Everything&lt;/a&gt; by David Graeber and David Wengrow. It felt like fresh air for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I stumbled upon his other books (thanks to my daughter), and Bullshit Jobs is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brilliant intro is his essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://strikemag.org/bullshit-jobs/&quot;&gt;On the Phenomenon of Bullshit Jobs&lt;/a&gt; he wrote in 2013. The article provoked massive reactions. The book goes much deeper, and draws from many conversations he had and other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a kind of book where one has to be able to re-think many ideas that are considered matter-of-fact. No, they are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#39;t pick up one thing. For sure, I cannot offer a summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pick up some - controversial indeed - takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yes, we could work only 20 hours per week - if there weren&#39;t bullshit jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No, capitalism doesn&#39;t make everything effective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many (most?) organizations have a similar structure as feudal society (with all the layers of feudal lords, retainers, and vassals).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Chat with GPT... why?</title>
    <link href="https://dchere.com/posts/chat-gpt-why/"/>
    <updated>2023-10-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://dchere.com/posts/chat-gpt-why/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Chat with GPT... why?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many many years ago I&#39;ve read a book about &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.debonogroup.com/services/core-programs/six-thinking-hats/&quot;&gt;Six Thinking Hats (r)&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; (even before it became trademarked thing... 🙈. This one has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/blog/productivity/six-thinking-hats&quot;&gt;nice explanation&lt;/a&gt; from Atlassian).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to think about various topic from as many angles as possible. Sometimes to question even the most basic assumptions everyone has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT can play interesting role in the process. It can be asked to summarize the topic and it does it well. But there is more - it can be asked to play some role, it can be asked to persuade, it can be asked to be critical. Do not take the twists, pros, cons, arguments with face value, but as a material to think about. After all is is &amp;quot;only chatGPT&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hey, GPT, what is Developer Experience?</title>
    <link href="https://dchere.com/posts/chat-gpt-dev-ex/"/>
    <updated>2023-10-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://dchere.com/posts/chat-gpt-dev-ex/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Hey, GPT, what is Developer Experience?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First (and hopefully not least) post about my chat with GPT. In this case about something I care about. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dchere.com/chat-gpt-why/&quot;&gt;Why as a chat with GPT?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;chat&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;2&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Tell me about developer experience (DevEx).&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;3&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Developer Experience (DevEx), often referred to as DX, is a term that encompasses the
                overall experience and satisfaction of software developers while they work on a
                project or use a particular set of tools, frameworks, or platforms. It focuses on
                creating an environment and set of practices that make development more efficient,
                enjoyable, and productive. Here are some key aspects of DevEx:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Tools and Technologies: DevEx involves providing developers with
                        user-friendly, efficient, and well-documented tools and technologies to help
                        them code, test, and deploy software more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Documentation: Comprehensive and clear documentation is crucial for
                        developers to understand and use APIs, libraries, and frameworks. Good
                        documentation is a key component of a positive DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Developer-Friendly APIs: APIs should be designed with the developer in mind,
                        ensuring they are intuitive, well-structured, and easy to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Debugging and Testing: Providing effective debugging and testing tools and
                        methodologies can significantly improve DevEx by helping developers find and
                        fix issues quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Collaboration and Communication: Effective collaboration tools and practices,
                        as well as open and transparent communication within development teams,
                        contribute to a better DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Performance and Optimization: Offering guidance and best practices for
                        optimizing code and system performance can enhance the developer&#39;s
                        experience by improving the efficiency of their work.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Onboarding and Training: Providing resources and processes for new developers
                        to get up to speed quickly is essential for a positive DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Community and Support: A supportive developer community, forums, and
                        responsive customer support can help developers overcome challenges and
                        contribute to a better overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Developer Empowerment: DevEx aims to empower developers by giving them the
                        tools, autonomy, and responsibility they need to make decisions and drive
                        the development process.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Feedback and Iteration: Continuous feedback loops and the ability to
                        incorporate developer feedback into the development process are important
                        aspects of DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A positive Developer Experience is vital in attracting and retaining talent,
                fostering innovation, and ultimately delivering high-quality software products.
                Developers who have a good experience are more likely to be motivated, productive,
                and satisfied with their work.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;4&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;What is the single most important benefit?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;5&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The single most important benefit of a positive Developer Experience (DevEx) is
                increased developer productivity. When developers have the tools, resources, and
                support they need to work efficiently and effectively, it results in faster
                development cycles, fewer roadblocks, and a higher output of quality code.
                Productivity gains translate to quicker software development, quicker
                time-to-market, and the ability to respond more rapidly to changing requirements and
                market demands.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;By focusing on DevEx and ensuring that developers have a conducive environment,
                organizations can:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Accelerate Software Development: Developers can write, test, and deploy code
                        more quickly, allowing for the rapid development of features and
                        applications.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Reduce Downtime: Efficient debugging and testing tools can help identify and
                        fix issues faster, reducing downtime and system outages.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Enhance Code Quality: When developers have access to resources and best
                        practices, they are more likely to produce high-quality, maintainable code.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Attract and Retain Talent: A positive DevEx can make an organization more
                        appealing to developers, leading to improved talent acquisition and
                        retention.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Increase Innovation: When developers are not bogged down by tooling and
                        administrative tasks, they can focus on creative problem-solving and
                        innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the most important benefit of a positive DevEx is that it empowers
                developers to do their best work efficiently, leading to better software and, by
                extension, improved business outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;6&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;We can often hear that developers are primadonnas, they should
deliver what is needed. How widespread is the idea of DX being important and beneficial?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;7&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The perception that developers are &quot;primadonnas&quot; or should solely focus on delivering
                what is needed without concern for Developer Experience (DevEx) is becoming
                increasingly outdated. In modern software development, there is a growing
                recognition of the importance and benefits of a positive DevEx. This shift in
                perspective is driven by several factors:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Competitive Talent Market: As the demand for skilled developers continues to
                        rise, organizations are realizing the importance of providing a positive
                        work environment to attract and retain top talent. DevEx plays a significant
                        role in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Agile and Continuous Delivery: Agile methodologies and continuous delivery
                        practices require faster development cycles and the ability to respond
                        quickly to changing requirements. DevEx is crucial in supporting these
                        approaches by improving developer productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;User-Centric Development: User experience and customer satisfaction are
                        paramount in software development. A better DevEx often results in better
                        software products, which, in turn, lead to increased user satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Innovation and Creativity: Developers are not just code writers; they are
                        problem solvers and innovators. Empowering them with the right tools and
                        resources fosters creativity and innovation in the development process.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Cost-Efficiency: Improving DevEx can lead to cost savings by reducing
                        development time, minimizing downtime, and decreasing the need for extensive
                        rework.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;Developer Well-Being: Prioritizing DevEx also acknowledges the importance of
                        developer well-being, which can contribute to higher job satisfaction,
                        reduced burnout, and improved mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;While there may still be organizations or individuals with the perspective that
                developers should solely focus on delivery, the prevailing trend in the software
                industry is to recognize the significance of DevEx. Successful tech companies,
                startups, and enterprises increasingly understand that by investing in a positive
                Developer Experience, they can achieve better software quality, innovation, and a
                competitive advantage in the market.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;8&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;What is the most widespread factor that makes developer unhappy
            and frustrated?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;9&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;One of the most widespread factors that can make developers unhappy and frustrated is
                &lt;strong&gt;poorly managed or constantly changing project requirements&lt;/strong&gt;. This
                often leads to what is commonly known as &quot;scope creep&quot; or frequent &quot;feature churn.&quot;
                When project requirements are not clearly defined, are constantly changing, or are
                inadequately communicated, it can have a detrimental effect on developer morale and
                job satisfaction. Here&#39;s why it&#39;s a major source of frustration:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Clarity&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers need clear and well-defined
                        requirements to do their job effectively. When requirements are vague or
                        subject to frequent changes, it becomes challenging for them to plan and
                        execute their work.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disrupted Workflow&lt;/strong&gt;: Frequent changes to project requirements
                        can disrupt the development workflow, causing developers to constantly shift
                        their focus and rework code, leading to inefficiency and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increased Stress&lt;/strong&gt;: Dealing with unclear or constantly
                        changing requirements can create a stressful environment for developers, as
                        they may feel pressured to meet shifting expectations and deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact on Quality&lt;/strong&gt;: Rapidly changing requirements can
                        compromise the quality of the software being developed, as there may be
                        insufficient time for thorough testing and refinement.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower Job Satisfaction&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers who consistently face
                        these challenges may become less satisfied with their work and more prone to
                        burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;To mitigate this issue and improve developer satisfaction, it&#39;s crucial for
                organizations to establish clear, stable, and well-communicated project
                requirements. Effective project management, communication, and a willingness to
                accommodate reasonable changes within a structured process can help address this
                common source of frustration in the development community.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;10&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Ok, but constant change is often cited as a part of the status quo.
            That everything is changing, and company has to be agile. Is it truth, and if so, how can they be managed simultaneously?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;11&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You&#39;re correct that change is often a part of the status quo in the software
                development industry, and companies need to be agile and adaptable to remain
                competitive in a dynamic market. However, managing constant change and maintaining a
                positive Developer Experience (DevEx) can be achieved simultaneously with careful
                planning and strategies. Here&#39;s how:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embrace Agile Practices&lt;/strong&gt;: Agile methodologies, such as Scrum
                        and Kanban, are designed to handle changing requirements effectively. By
                        implementing agile practices, development teams can adapt to evolving needs
                        while maintaining a structured and manageable development process.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effective Communication&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensure that there is open and
                        transparent communication between product managers, project stakeholders,
                        and development teams. Frequent and clear communication helps in
                        understanding and managing changing requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prioritize and Plan&lt;/strong&gt;: It&#39;s crucial to prioritize changes and
                        new features based on their impact and importance. Detailed planning and a
                        well-defined roadmap can help developers anticipate and manage changes more
                        effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iterative Development&lt;/strong&gt;: Use iterative development processes
                        where features are developed in small, incremental steps. This approach
                        allows for flexibility and adaptation as new information or requirements
                        emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Feedback&lt;/strong&gt;: Establish mechanisms for collecting
                        feedback from end-users and stakeholders throughout the development process.
                        This feedback loop helps ensure that changes align with actual user needs
                        and expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DevOps Practices&lt;/strong&gt;: Implement DevOps practices to streamline
                        deployment and ensure that code changes can be quickly and safely integrated
                        into production. This reduces friction in responding to changing market
                        requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automated Testing&lt;/strong&gt;: Invest in automated testing to maintain
                        software quality even when dealing with frequent changes. Automated testing
                        can catch regressions and issues quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developer Empowerment&lt;/strong&gt;: Empower developers to be part of the
                        decision-making process and encourage them to suggest improvements and
                        adaptations to meet evolving market demands.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Balancing the need for agility with the desire for a positive Developer Experience
                can be challenging, but it&#39;s achievable by creating a culture that embraces change
                and provides developers with the tools and support they need to manage change
                effectively. It&#39;s also important to remember that while change is constant, a
                well-structured and clear change management process can help developers adapt
                without excessive frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;12&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Who in the company should be responsible for DX?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;13&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The responsibility for Developer Experience (DevEx) should be shared across various
                roles and departments within a company. While it&#39;s not the sole responsibility of a
                single individual, there are key stakeholders who play significant roles in shaping
                and improving DevEx:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product Managers&lt;/strong&gt;: Product managers are often responsible for
                        defining the product or feature requirements. They should work closely with
                        developers to ensure that requirements are clear and align with user needs.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engineering and Development Teams&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers themselves are
                        crucial stakeholders in DevEx. They should have a say in tool selection,
                        workflow processes, and the overall development environment. Their input is
                        invaluable for identifying pain points and suggesting improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UX/UI Designers&lt;/strong&gt;: User Experience (UX) and User Interface
                        (UI) designers play a vital role in creating interfaces and designs that are
                        developer-friendly and align with user expectations. Collaboration with
                        developers is essential to ensure designs are implementable.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DevOps and IT Teams&lt;/strong&gt;: DevOps and IT teams are responsible for
                        infrastructure, deployment, and operations. They can contribute to a better
                        DevEx by ensuring smooth deployments and providing effective tools for
                        managing infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality Assurance Teams&lt;/strong&gt;: QA teams should work in conjunction
                        with developers to create effective testing processes and tools to catch
                        issues early, ensuring a smooth development process.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical Writers&lt;/strong&gt;: Technical writers play a key role in
                        producing documentation that aids developers in understanding APIs,
                        libraries, and other technical resources.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Human Resources and People Operations&lt;/strong&gt;: HR and People
                        Operations departments can foster a positive work culture that supports
                        developer well-being, job satisfaction, and professional growth.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Executive Leadership&lt;/strong&gt;: Company leadership should recognize
                        the importance of DevEx and allocate resources and support for its
                        improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Managers&lt;/strong&gt;: If the company has a developer community
                        or open-source projects, community managers can help create an engaging and
                        supportive environment.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Feedback Mechanisms&lt;/strong&gt;: Implement feedback
                        mechanisms, such as regular surveys or meetings, where developers can
                        provide input on their experiences and suggest improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;In summary, DevEx is a collective effort that involves various stakeholders in a
                company. Effective collaboration between these roles is essential to ensure a
                positive Developer Experience and foster a productive, innovative, and satisfied
                developer community.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;14&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Collective effort sounds nice, but when everybody is responsible, then
            nobody is. What are the practices today? Is there often a DX position, or most often not?
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;15&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You make a valid point about shared responsibility potentially leading to a situation
                where &quot;everyone is responsible, so nobody is.&quot; In practice, the approach to managing
                Developer Experience (DevEx) can vary from one organization to another. While some
                companies have dedicated DX roles or teams, others incorporate DevEx
                responsibilities into existing roles and teams. Here&#39;s an overview of the common
                practices today:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dedicated DX Roles&lt;/strong&gt;: Some organizations have recognized the
                        importance of DevEx and have introduced dedicated positions like &quot;Developer
                        Experience Manager&quot; or &quot;Developer Advocate.&quot; These individuals are
                        responsible for championing the needs of developers, collecting feedback,
                        and driving improvements in tools, processes, and documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-Functional Teams&lt;/strong&gt;: Many companies adopt a
                        cross-functional team approach, where members from different roles
                        collaborate to improve DevEx. These teams include developers, product
                        managers, designers, and others who collectively focus on creating a better
                        development environment.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product Teams&lt;/strong&gt;: In organizations where DevEx is closely tied
                        to product development, product managers and engineers take on the
                        responsibility of ensuring that the products and tools they create are
                        developer-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open-Source Projects&lt;/strong&gt;: In open-source projects, maintainers
                        often pay special attention to DevEx since they rely on a broader community
                        of contributors. They may have designated roles like &quot;Community Manager&quot; who
                        work to improve DevEx for contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feedback Loops&lt;/strong&gt;: Regardless of the specific roles in place,
                        feedback loops from developers are common. Regular surveys, meetings, and
                        forums are used to collect input from developers, and this feedback drives
                        DevEx improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The approach a company takes to DevEx management can be influenced by its size,
                industry, and specific needs. Smaller startups might not have dedicated DX roles but
                place emphasis on DevEx through cross-functional teams, while larger enterprises
                might have dedicated roles due to the scale and complexity of their projects.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the key is to ensure that someone within the organization, whether it&#39;s a
                specific role or a collective effort, is responsible for continuously evaluating and
                improving DevEx to meet the evolving needs of developers and the organization&#39;s
                goals.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;16&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;DX is about developer happiness. But this cannot be measured. How can we evaluate DX efforts? Management usually wants some numbers. Are there any studies or researches?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;17&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You&#39;re correct that measuring developer happiness, which is a crucial aspect of
                Developer Experience (DevEx), can be challenging as it&#39;s subjective and can vary
                from one individual to another. However, there are several indirect and quantitative
                ways to evaluate and assess DX efforts. While there might not be one universally
                accepted metric for DevEx, you can use a combination of the following methods:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surveys and Feedback&lt;/strong&gt;: Regularly conduct surveys and gather
                        feedback from developers on various aspects of their experience. Ask
                        questions about tool satisfaction, workflow efficiency, and overall job
                        satisfaction. This feedback can provide valuable insights.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Metrics&lt;/strong&gt;: Measure development time and productivity.
                        Look for trends in how quickly developers can deliver features or resolve
                        issues before and after DX improvements. Faster development and issue
                        resolution can indicate improved DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bug and Issue Tracking&lt;/strong&gt;: Monitor the number of bugs and
                        issues reported by developers. A reduction in the number of issues related
                        to development tools, processes, or workflows can be a positive sign.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deployment Frequency&lt;/strong&gt;: Track how frequently code is deployed
                        to production. Improved DevEx can lead to more frequent and smoother
                        deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code Quality Metrics&lt;/strong&gt;: Use code quality metrics, such as code
                        reviews, code maintainability, and bug recurrence rates, to assess the
                        impact of DevEx on code quality.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retention and Recruitment&lt;/strong&gt;: Monitor developer turnover rates.
                        A low turnover rate can indicate higher job satisfaction due to a positive
                        DevEx. Similarly, the ability to attract new talent can be a sign of a good
                        DevEx reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Engagement&lt;/strong&gt;: If applicable, evaluate community
                        engagement in open-source projects or developer forums. Increased community
                        participation can be a sign of a thriving DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation Metrics&lt;/strong&gt;: Assess the usage of documentation and
                        support resources. Analyze the number of visits, searches, and user feedback
                        related to documentation quality.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;While there might not be comprehensive studies or one-size-fits-all metrics for
                DevEx, organizations can tailor their evaluation methods to fit their specific needs
                and goals. Combining both quantitative and qualitative data, along with feedback
                from developers, can provide a more holistic understanding of the effectiveness of
                DX efforts. The ultimate goal is to make data-driven decisions and continuously
                improve the developer experience within the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;18&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;You mentioned “measure development time and productivity”. Aren’t
the box-checking, time reporting, assigning pointless points to tasks, etc. the biggest reasons for developer frustration?
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;19&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You&#39;re absolutely right that some of the practices associated with measuring
                development time and productivity, such as excessive time reporting, assigning
                arbitrary points to tasks (common in Agile methodologies like story points), and
                excessive &quot;box-checking,&quot; can indeed contribute to developer frustration. Developers
                often find these practices burdensome and counterproductive, as they can add
                administrative overhead and hinder the creative and problem-solving aspects of their
                work.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The key is to strike a balance between measuring productivity and ensuring a positive
                Developer Experience (DevEx). While it&#39;s important to have some metrics to assess
                efficiency and identify bottlenecks, it&#39;s equally important to avoid overburdening
                developers with excessive reporting and administrative tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Here are some best practices to balance productivity measurement with developer
                satisfaction:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplify Metrics&lt;/strong&gt;: Choose a small set of meaningful and
                        relevant metrics that provide insights into productivity without creating
                        unnecessary overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate Reporting&lt;/strong&gt;: Whenever possible, automate the
                        collection of data for productivity metrics, reducing the need for manual
                        reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on Outcomes&lt;/strong&gt;: Emphasize the outcomes of development
                        efforts rather than just tracking the time spent. Metrics related to feature
                        completion, code quality, and user satisfaction can be more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encourage Self-Reporting&lt;/strong&gt;: Give developers some autonomy in
                        how they report their progress. Allow them to provide input on the metrics
                        they find most relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid Micro-Management&lt;/strong&gt;: Avoid micromanaging developers with
                        constant oversight. Trust them to manage their time and tasks effectively.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular Feedback&lt;/strong&gt;: Provide developers with feedback based on
                        metrics, and use it as a tool for improvement rather than punishment.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Communication&lt;/strong&gt;: Create an environment where developers
                        feel comfortable discussing concerns about metrics and administrative
                        practices. Act on their feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The goal is to strike a balance between productivity measurement and a positive
                DevEx. It&#39;s essential to find methods that allow for effective project management
                while minimizing practices that lead to frustration and hinder creativity and
                problem-solving, which are central to the developer&#39;s role.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;20&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;So imagine that you are CEO, have heard about DX, and you like the idea about having happy developers because it will make your company faster, better, and more valuable (because of people). What would you do as a first step?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;21&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;If I were a CEO and I wanted to prioritize Developer Experience (DevEx) to make my
                company more efficient, innovative, and valuable, my first step would be to create a
                clear plan of action. Here&#39;s what I would do:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledge the Importance&lt;/strong&gt;: I would communicate to the
                        entire organization that DevEx is a priority and that it directly impacts
                        our ability to deliver high-quality software, attract and retain talent, and
                        respond to market demands.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appoint a DevEx Champion&lt;/strong&gt;: I would designate a DevEx leader
                        or team responsible for driving DevEx initiatives and improvements. This
                        could be a dedicated Developer Experience Manager or a cross-functional
                        team.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gather Developer Feedback&lt;/strong&gt;: I would initiate a
                        feedback-gathering process, involving surveys, one-on-one discussions, and
                        open forums to understand the current pain points and challenges faced by
                        developers.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set Clear Goals&lt;/strong&gt;: Establish clear, measurable goals for
                        improving DevEx. These goals should align with the company&#39;s broader
                        objectives, such as reducing time-to-market or increasing software quality.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prioritize Key Areas&lt;/strong&gt;: Based on the feedback and goals, I
                        would identify and prioritize the most critical areas that require
                        attention. This could include improving tooling, streamlining processes,
                        enhancing documentation, or addressing cultural issues.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allocate Resources&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensure that the DevEx leader or team has
                        the necessary resources and support to implement changes effectively. This
                        might involve budget allocation, additional staffing, or tools and
                        technology investments.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a DevEx Roadmap&lt;/strong&gt;: Develop a roadmap with a timeline
                        for implementing DevEx improvements. This roadmap should include specific
                        projects and initiatives, as well as milestones for tracking progress.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foster a Culture of DevEx&lt;/strong&gt;: Encourage a culture of DevEx
                        throughout the organization. This means promoting collaboration,
                        transparency, and open communication between development teams and other
                        departments.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measure and Iterate&lt;/strong&gt;: Implement metrics and key performance
                        indicators (KPIs) to track the impact of DevEx improvements. Continuously
                        collect feedback and iterate on the DevEx initiatives as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celebrate Successes&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognize and celebrate achievements
                        related to DevEx improvements to reinforce the importance of a positive
                        Developer Experience within the company.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular Updates&lt;/strong&gt;: Provide regular updates to the organization
                        about the progress of DevEx initiatives and the positive impact on projects,
                        teams, and business outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empower Developers&lt;/strong&gt;: Give developers the autonomy to make
                        decisions and recommendations related to their work environment, tools, and
                        processes.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;By taking these steps, as a CEO, I would demonstrate a commitment to enhancing
                Developer Experience and set the foundation for a more efficient, innovative, and
                valuable company driven by a happy and productive developer community.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;22&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;You mentioned “empower developers”  for the second time. Can you explain a bit?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;23&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Certainly, empowering developers is about giving them the autonomy, authority, and
                responsibility to make decisions and take ownership of their work. It&#39;s a crucial
                aspect of fostering a positive Developer Experience (DevEx) and a productive
                development environment. Here&#39;s what it means and why it&#39;s important:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decision-Making Autonomy&lt;/strong&gt;: Empowered developers have the
                        freedom to make decisions about their work, such as choosing the right
                        tools, technologies, and approaches for solving problems. This autonomy
                        allows them to leverage their expertise and creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem-Solving Responsibility&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers are often closest
                        to the technical challenges they face. Empowering them means trusting them
                        to identify issues and find solutions. It encourages them to take
                        responsibility for problem-solving and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Influence in Project Direction&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers should have a say
                        in project direction and prioritization. They can provide input on feature
                        roadmaps, architecture choices, and technical debt reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code Ownership&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers take ownership of the code they
                        write. This means they are responsible for the quality, maintainability, and
                        performance of their code. Code ownership can lead to a sense of pride and
                        accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuous Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;: Empowered developers can propose
                        improvements to processes, workflows, and tools. They actively contribute to
                        making the development environment more efficient and developer-friendly.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning and Professional Growth&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers should have the
                        freedom to pursue learning opportunities, explore new technologies, and grow
                        in their careers. Empowerment includes supporting their professional
                        development.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Communication&lt;/strong&gt;: Encouraging open communication and
                        feedback channels between developers and management is crucial. Developers
                        should feel comfortable sharing their ideas, concerns, and feedback without
                        fear of repercussions.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Empowering developers aligns with the principles of agile and DevOps, which emphasize
                collaboration, ownership, and continuous improvement. When developers are empowered,
                they are more motivated, engaged, and likely to contribute their best to the
                organization. This, in turn, leads to a positive DevEx and ultimately benefits the
                company by accelerating development, improving software quality, and fostering a
                cohesive and innovative development culture.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;24&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;CIOs within an organization can be viewed as best candidates from the top management) to lead the DX initiative. But it will be another initiative upon all his other responsibilities and may lead to not pushing it forward enough. Even a kind of threat that CIOs might blamed for failing the role if the first dev survey shows a lot of frustration. What to do with that?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;25&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;You bring up a valid concern. While the Chief Information Officer (CIO) can be a
                suitable candidate to lead a Developer Experience (DevEx) initiative due to their
                understanding of technology and its impact on the organization, it&#39;s important to
                consider their existing responsibilities and the potential for conflicts or
                perceptions of failure.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;To address this challenge, here are some strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designate a DevEx Champion&lt;/strong&gt;: Consider designating a DevEx
                        leader or team that works in collaboration with the CIO. This can alleviate
                        the burden on the CIO and ensure that DevEx receives dedicated attention.
                        The DevEx leader/team can focus on implementing and driving DevEx
                        improvements, while the CIO provides support and alignment with broader
                        organizational goals.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set Realistic Expectations&lt;/strong&gt;: Clearly communicate the
                        expectations for the DevEx initiative and the balance between existing CIO
                        responsibilities and the new initiative. Acknowledge that DevEx improvements
                        may take time, and the first survey or feedback round might uncover areas
                        for improvement. Emphasize the long-term benefits for the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular Progress Updates&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensure that there is regular
                        reporting and updates on the progress of the DevEx initiative. This includes
                        sharing the positive outcomes, even if there are initial challenges.
                        Transparency in communication helps in managing expectations and
                        demonstrating commitment to the initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborate Across Departments&lt;/strong&gt;: Encourage collaboration
                        between the IT department (led by the CIO) and other departments, like HR or
                        the product management team, to share the responsibility for DevEx.
                        Collaborative efforts can help distribute the workload and ensure a
                        well-rounded approach to DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celebrate Small Wins&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognize and celebrate small
                        achievements and milestones in the DevEx initiative. Acknowledging progress,
                        even if it&#39;s gradual, can help maintain motivation and show that the
                        initiative is making a positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Involve Developers&lt;/strong&gt;: Include developers in the
                        decision-making process and let them have a say in how the DevEx initiative
                        is structured and executed. Their input can be valuable in identifying
                        priorities and shaping the direction of the initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn and Iterate&lt;/strong&gt;: Use the feedback from the initial
                        developer survey as a starting point for improvement. Demonstrate a
                        commitment to learning from the feedback and iterate on the initiative to
                        address developer frustrations and concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;In summary, while the CIO can be a suitable leader for a DevEx initiative, it&#39;s
                important to address the challenges you&#39;ve mentioned through collaborative efforts,
                clear communication, and a commitment to long-term improvement. The key is to create
                an environment where DevEx is recognized as a shared responsibility throughout the
                organization, not solely the burden of one individual.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;26&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;Imagine overworked, frustrated developers in the current state at some company. They should fill in another survey about DX. They can imagine that it will be another “compliance game to be nice” and will not have the will to participate and take it seriously. How to overcome that and demonstrate that the company started to care about that part of the working environment?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;27&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Engaging overworked and frustrated developers to participate in a Developer
                Experience (DevEx) survey, especially when they may be skeptical of the process, can
                be challenging. To overcome this skepticism and demonstrate a genuine commitment to
                improving the working environment, consider the following strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparent Communication&lt;/strong&gt;: Communicate openly with
                        developers about the purpose of the survey and its potential impact. Address
                        their concerns and skepticism directly. Let them know that their feedback is
                        crucial for identifying and addressing issues.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anonymous Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;: Assure developers that the survey will be
                        anonymous, and their responses will not be used against them. Anonymity can
                        encourage more honest and candid feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listening Sessions&lt;/strong&gt;: Organize listening sessions or focus
                        groups where developers can voice their concerns in person or virtually.
                        These sessions can provide a more personal and interactive platform for
                        feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Involvement in Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;: Make it clear that the company is
                        not just seeking feedback but is genuinely interested in finding solutions.
                        Invite developers to be part of the process of improving DevEx and encourage
                        them to propose ideas for change.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immediate Action&lt;/strong&gt;: As a show of commitment, prioritize
                        addressing some of the most pressing issues raised in the survey as soon as
                        possible. Demonstrating that the company is taking action can help build
                        trust.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feedback Loops&lt;/strong&gt;: Establish a feedback loop, so developers can
                        see how their input is leading to changes. Provide regular updates on the
                        progress of DevEx improvements and demonstrate that their voices are being
                        heard.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empowerment&lt;/strong&gt;: Encourage developers to take ownership of DevEx
                        improvements. Provide resources and support for them to initiate changes in
                        their own workflows or tools. This empowers them to be part of the solution.
                    &lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education&lt;/strong&gt;: Educate developers about the potential benefits
                        of a positive DevEx. Explain how it can lead to reduced workloads, improved
                        code quality, and ultimately a more pleasant working environment.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appreciation and Recognition&lt;/strong&gt;: Show appreciation for their
                        participation and feedback. Recognize and reward developers for their
                        contributions to the DevEx initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long-Term Commitment&lt;/strong&gt;: Emphasize that improving DevEx is not
                        a one-time effort but a long-term commitment. DevEx is an ongoing journey,
                        and the company is dedicated to continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;By taking these steps and demonstrating a sincere commitment to improving Developer
                Experience, the company can work to overcome skepticism and engage developers in a
                constructive and collaborative way. This can lead to a more positive and productive
                working environment over time.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;28&quot; data-role=&quot;user&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;What could be the reason for that current state: overworked frustrated developers?&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;turn-wrapper&quot; data-turn=&quot;29&quot; data-role=&quot;assistant&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;There can be several reasons for a state of overworked and frustrated developers
                within an organization. It&#39;s important to identify and address these issues to
                improve Developer Experience (DevEx). Some common reasons for such a state may
                include:&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Excessive Workload&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers are often under pressure to
                        deliver more work than they can reasonably handle within a given timeframe.
                        Unrealistic workloads can lead to stress and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tight Deadlines&lt;/strong&gt;: Frequent, unrealistic deadlines can make
                        developers feel rushed and unable to maintain the quality of their work.
                        This constant pressure can lead to frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inadequate Resources&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers may lack the necessary
                        tools, infrastructure, or resources to effectively perform their tasks. This
                        can slow down development and lead to frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poorly Defined Requirements&lt;/strong&gt;: Unclear or constantly changing
                        project requirements can make it difficult for developers to plan and
                        execute their work efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inefficient Processes&lt;/strong&gt;: Cumbersome development processes,
                        excessive administrative tasks, or outdated workflows can slow down
                        developers and lead to frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Autonomy&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers may feel that they have little
                        control or autonomy over their work, which can be demoralizing and
                        frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inadequate Communication&lt;/strong&gt;: Poor communication between teams,
                        departments, or stakeholders can lead to misunderstandings, delays, and
                        increased frustration for developers.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of Recognition&lt;/strong&gt;: A lack of recognition or appreciation
                        for the efforts of developers can lead to low morale and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burnout&lt;/strong&gt;: Constant pressure and overwork can lead to burnout,
                        which can significantly impact developer satisfaction and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inadequate Training and Support&lt;/strong&gt;: Developers may lack access
                        to training or support to stay up to date with new technologies and best
                        practices, leading to frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conflict or Toxic Culture&lt;/strong&gt;: Workplace conflicts or a toxic
                        company culture can create a negative working environment that contributes
                        to frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compensation and Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: If developers feel their
                        compensation and benefits are not competitive or fair, it can lead to
                        dissatisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Addressing these issues may involve a combination of changes to processes, resource
                allocation, communication, workload management, and a focus on creating a supportive
                and collaborative working environment. It&#39;s important for organizations to actively
                listen to their developers, address their concerns, and make ongoing efforts to
                improve the overall working conditions and DevEx.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cyanotype - joy of the moment</title>
    <link href="https://dchere.com/posts/cyano1/"/>
    <updated>2023-09-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://dchere.com/posts/cyano1/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Cyanotype and the Joy of The Moment&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_small_branch-CD65KljUjz-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_small_branch-CD65KljUjz-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_small_branch-CD65KljUjz-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_small_branch-CD65KljUjz-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_small_branch-CD65KljUjz-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;1536&quot; alt=&quot;Cyanotype - moment&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyanotype&quot;&gt;Cyanotype&lt;/a&gt; is a joyful activity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you paint some chemicals on the paper and let it dry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;then you lay on the paper some things (leaves etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leave it on the direct sun for a couple of minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the last step is washing the paper in the water (developing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was in the shadow (like masked by leaves) becomes white-ish. Parts exposed to the sunrays, becomes beautifully blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_leaf-U73gZwcoq9-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_leaf-U73gZwcoq9-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_leaf-U73gZwcoq9-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_leaf-U73gZwcoq9-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_leaf-U73gZwcoq9-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;1536&quot; alt=&quot;Cyanotype - going bigger&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is so much space for unintended effects, and randomness (when the wind blows and moves your leaves). I love it. The result is not mine but done by chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_2colors_fish-eC3ajPMvJ4-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_2colors_fish-eC3ajPMvJ4-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_2colors_fish-eC3ajPMvJ4-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_2colors_fish-eC3ajPMvJ4-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_2colors_fish-eC3ajPMvJ4-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;862&quot; alt=&quot;Cyanotype - making it 2 color&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a way to make it yellow and blue. The part of the image that takes a bath in baking soda for 8 hours turns yellow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is much more effort than taking a picture by mobile phone, 😉 but it is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_sunsurfing-6eHUQVoGwP-700.webp 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_sunsurfing-6eHUQVoGwP-1152.webp 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
&lt;source type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; srcset=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_sunsurfing-6eHUQVoGwP-700.jpeg 700w, https://dchere.com/img/cyano_sunsurfing-6eHUQVoGwP-1152.jpeg 1152w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 756px) 80vw, (min-width: 757px) 576px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://dchere.com/img/cyano_sunsurfing-6eHUQVoGwP-1152.webp&quot; width=&quot;1152&quot; height=&quot;1642&quot; alt=&quot;Cyanotype - surfer&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can even do a kind of photos.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
